Good morning everyone.
各位同学 早上好
Today we are going to do some algorithms, back to algorithms,
今天我们将学习一些算法 说到算法
and we are going to use a lot of the,
我们将用到很多简单的数学知识
well, some of the simpler mathematics
其实也没有太多
that we developed last class
这些数学知识我们上节课都学过
like the master theorem for solving recurrences.
比如解决递归问题的主定理
We are going to use this a lot.
这个我们将会用到很多
Because we are going to talk about recursive algorithms today.
因为今天我们讨论的是递归算法
And so we will find their running time
通过这个主定理
using the master theorem.
我们可以计算出它们的时间复杂度
This is just the same as it was last time, I hope,
除非是我搞错了
unless I made a mistake.
这里写的还是和上次的一样
A couple of reminders.
提醒大家几件事
You should all go to recitation on Friday.
你们所有人必须在星期五的时候来上复习课
That is required.
这是最低要求
If you want to,
如果你愿意的话
you can go to homework lab on Sunday.
你可以在星期天的时候到作业实验室来
That may be a good excuse for you
这可能需要你
to actually work on your problem set a few hours early.
提前一些时间来完成作业
Well, actually, it's still on Wednesday
其实作业实验室一直开到星期三
so you have lots of time.
所以你的时间还是很充足的
And there is no class on Monday.
还有 星期一没课
It is the holiday known as Student Holiday,
这是所谓的学生假日
so don't come.
这天就别来了
Today we are going to cover something called Divide and Conquer.
今天我们将学习分治法
also known as divide and rule.
也叫做分治法
or divide et impera for those of you who know Latin,
或者是拉丁语 "divide et impera"
which is a tried and tested way
顾名思义 分治法是把一片领土分解
of conquering a land
分解为若干块小部分
by dividing it into sections of some kind.
然后一块块的占领征服
It could be different political factions,
被分解的可以是不同的政治派别
different whatever.
或是其他不同的什么
And then somehow making them no longer like each other.
然后让他们彼此异化
Like starting a family feud
就像策划了一次家庭内部斗争
is always a good method.
这是个不错的策略
You should remember this on your quiz.
你在考试的时候得记住这个比喻
I'm kidding.
开玩笑哈
And if you can separate this big power structure
如果你能把一个大的结构
into little power structures
分解成一些小结构
such that you dominate each little power structure
然后去掌握每一个小的结构
then you can conquer all of them individually,
最终你就可以掌握小结构的和
as long as you make sure they don't get back together.
只要你不让它们再次结合
That is divide and conquer as practiced, say, by the British.
这就是英国人的军事策略
But today we are going to do divide and conquer as practiced in
但我们今天所讲的是这本书
Cormen, Leiserson, Rivest and Stein
《算法导论》
or every other algorithm textbook.
或者其他算法书中的分治法
This is a very basic
这是一个非常基础的
and very powerful algorithm design technique.
而且是非常有效的算法设计方法
So, this is our first real algorithm design experience.
这是我们学习的第一个算法设计方法
We are still sort of mostly in the analysis mode,
现在我们还是在算法分析阶段
but we are going to do some actual design.
接下来我们就要开始学习算法设计
We're going to cover maybe only three or four major design techniques.
我们将要学习3到4个算法设计方法
This is one of them,
这是其中之一
so it is really important.
所以这个分治法非常重要
And it will lead to all sorts of recurrences,
并且分治法将引出所有类型的递归
so we will get to use everything from last class
我们将用到上节课学的所有的东西
and see why it is useful.
看看它们为什么这么有用
As you might expect, the first step in divide-and-conquer is
正如你所想 分治法的第一步是分
divide and the second step is conquer.
第二步是治
But you may not have guessed that there are three steps.
你可能还想不到有第三步
And I am leaving some blank space here,
我在这留下了些空行
so you should, too.
你应该也空出来
Divide-and-conquer is an algorithmic technique.
分治法是一个算法策略
You are given some big problem you want to solve,
让你去解决一个很大的问题
you don't really know how to solve it in an efficient way,
你根本不知道如何去有效的解决它
so you are going to split it up into subproblems.
你可以将它分解成一些子问题
That is the divide.
这就是"分"
You are going to divide that problem,
你可以把一个问题
or more precisely the instance of that problem,
或者精确的说 一个问题的实例
the particular instance of that problem you have into subproblems.
一个问题的特殊实例划分成若干子问题
And those subproblems should be smaller in some sense.
并且这些子问题在一定程度上更小了
And smaller means normally that
更小了就是说
the value of n is smaller than it was in the original problem.
原问题的规模n更小了
So, you sort of made some progress.
至此 你完成了第一步
Now you have one,
现在你有一个
or more likely you have several subproblems you need to solve.
或者好几个子问题需要解决
Each of them is smaller.
每个子问题的规模更小
So, you recursively solve each subproblem.
你递归的去解决每个子问题
That is the conquer step.
这就是第二步"治"
You conquer each subproblem recursively.
递归的解决每一个子问题
And then somehow you combine those solutions into
然后把这些子问题的解
a solution for the whole problem.
合并成为整个大问题的解
So, this is the general divide-and-conquer paradigm.
这就是一般的分治法的步骤
And lots of algorithms fit it.
很多算法都用到了它
You have already seen one algorithm that fits this paradigm,
你们已经学过一个采用分治策略的算法
if you can remember. Merge sort, good.
有人记得吗 归并排序
Wow, you are all awake.
非常好 你们还没睡着
I'm impressed.
我太感动了
So, we saw merge sort.
好 我们来看看归并排序
And, if I am clever, I could fit it in this space.
我觉着这块应该能写的下
Sure. Let's be clever.
好 就在这块写吧
A quick review on merge sort.
我们来复习下归并排序
Phrased in this 1, 2, 3 kind of method.
它也有分治法的三个步骤
The first step was to divide your array into two halves.
第一步是将待排序的数组一分为二
This really doesn't mean anything because you just sort of think,
你得在大脑中模拟出这样的情景
oh, I will pretend my array is divided into two halves.you don't have ..
好 现在我已经把数组一分为二了
There is no work here.
这一步很简单
This is zero time. You just look at your array.
这是第一步
Here is your array.
假设这个是待排序的数组
I guess maybe you compute n/2 and take the floor.
我想你可能算出了n/2
That takes constant time.
这个的计算时间是个常量
And you say OK, I am pretending my array is
好 假设现在这个数组
now divided into the left part and the right part.
已经分成了左半边和右半边
And then the interesting part is that you recursively solve each one.
接下来是递归的处理每一个部分
That's the conquer.
这就是"治"这一步
We recursively sort each subarray.
我们递归的对每一个子数组进行排序
And then the third step is to combine those solutions.
第三步就是合并
And so here we really see what this means.
现在一目了然了
We now have a sorted version of this array by induction.
就像前面所说 这一部分已经有序了
We have a sorted version of this array by induction.
这一部分也有序了
We now want the sorted version of the whole array.
现在需要使整个数组都有序
And we saw that was the merge problem, merging two sorted arrays.
这是合并问题 合并两个有序数组
And that we saw how to do in linear time, order n time.
我们已经知道这在线性时间n内可以完成
I am not going to repeat that,
我不想重复这个知识点
but the point is it falls into that framework.
但是它现在就在我们讨论的范围内
I want to write the running time and merge sort as a recurrence.
我现在写出归并排序算法的时间复杂度
You have already seen the recurrence,
你们已经学过这个递归算法
you have already been told the solution,
知道是怎么回事
but now we actually know how to solve it.
现在应该知道如何设计递归算法
And, furthermore,
好 进一步说
every algorithm that follows the divide-and-conquer paradigm
每一个符合分治策略的算法
will have a recurrence of pretty much the same form,
几乎都有相似形式的递归出现
very much like our good friend the master method.
就像我们的好朋友 主定理
Let's do it for merge sort where we sort of already
我们把它应用在归并排序中
know the answer and get a bit of practice.
我们做点练习
This is the merge sort recurrence.
这是归并排序的递归表达式
You should know and love this recurrence
你应该记住它 并且爱上它
because it comes up all over the place.
因为它无处不在
It comes from this general approach
它从这个一般性方法归纳而来
by just seeing what are the sizes of the subproblems
方法是计算子问题的规模
you are solving and how many there are
你需要知道
and how much extra work you are doing.
有多少计算量
You have here the size of the subproblems.
还有子问题的规模
It happens here that both subproblems have the same size roughly.
归并排序的子问题规模差不多一样
There is this sloppiness that we have,
有一个我没说清的问题
which really should be T of floor of n over 2 plus T of ceiling of n over 2.
就是跟 T(n/2) 的上下界
And when you go to recitation on Friday you will see why that is OK,
星期五的复习课我会讲为什么是这样
the floors and ceilings don't matter.
下界上界可以略去
There is a theorem you can prove that that's happy.
有个证明简单的定理可以用
You can assume that n is a power of 2,
现在你可以假设n是2的幂次方
but we are just going to assume that for now.
我们现在就这样假设
We just have two problems with size n over 2.
现有两个问题 规模都是n/2
This 2 is the number of subproblems.
这个2是子问题的数目
And this order n is all the extra work we are doing.
这个n是附加的计算量
Now, what is the extra work potentially?
附加的计算量有哪些
Well, the conquering is always just recursion.
分解过程一般就是递归
There is sort of no work there except this lead part.
除了开头 这一步没有什么计算量
The dividing in this case is trivial,
这个例子中分解这一步不是很有意思
but in general it might involve some work.
一般来说 这一步有一些附加计算量
And the combining here involves linear work.
合并也有些线性的计算量
So, this is the divide-and-conquer running times.
所以 这个是分治法的运行时间
So, this is the nonrecursive work.
这一部分没有包括递归的计算量
And that is generally
这就是如何把运用分治法
how you convert a divide-and-conquer algorithm into a recurrence.
写出递归的一般步骤
It's really easy and you usually get to apply the master method.
这个简单 一般还会用到主定理
Here we are in Case 2. Very good.
现在是哪种情况 第二个 很好
This is Case 2. And k is zero here.
这是第二种情况k等于0
And so in the recursion tree,
在递归树中
all of the costs are roughly the same.
每一个结点的时间复杂度都差不多
They are all n to the log base b of a.
都是n^logb(a)
Here n to the log base 2 of 2 is just n.
n^log2(2) 还是n
So these are equal.
这两个式子是相等的
We get an extra log factor
还有个log因子
because of the number of levels in the recursion tree.
因为递归树有好几层
Remember the intuition behind the master method.
记住主方法中的直觉
This is n log n.
这里得出 nlogn
and that is good.
这很好
Merge sort is a fast sorting algorithm n log n.
归并排序是个快速的nlogn排序算法
Insertion sort was n squared.
插入排序的复杂度是n的平方
In some sense, n log n is the best you can do.
一般来说 nlogn是最快的了
We will cover that in two lectures from now,
我们得用两节课的时间来讲这个问题
but just foreshadowing.
现在只是个铺垫
Today we are going to do different divide-and-conquer algorithms.
今天我们要学几个分治算法
Sorting is one problem.
排序只是其中之一
There are all sorts of problems we might want to solve.
有各种各样的问题需要我们去解决
It turns out a lot of them you can apply divide-and-conquer to.
其中有一些问题可以使用分治法
Not every problem.
但不是每一个都行
Like how to wake up in the morning,
就像早上起床
it's not so easy to solve a divide-and-conquer,
使用分治法不是那么简单的
although maybe that's a good problem set problem.
即使这个问题是个简单问题
The next divide-and-conquer algorithm
这是另一个使用分治法的算法
we are going to look at is even simpler than sorting,
这个算法比排序还简单
even simpler than merge sort,
比归并排序还简单
but it drives home the point of when you have only one subproblem.
这个算法只有一个子问题
How many people have seen binary search before?
有没有人知道二分查找算法
Anyone hasn't? One, OK.
一个也没有 只有一个
I will go very quickly then.
我快点讲
You have some element x.
设某个元素为x
You want to find x in a sorted array.
你需要在一个已排序的数组中找到这个x
How many people had not seen it before they saw it in recitation?
有多少人在没上复习课之前见过这个算法
No one, OK. Good.
没有 很好
You have seen it in another class,
在另外一节课上你们会学到这个算法
probably 6.001 or something.
好像是6.001
Very good. You took the prerequisites.
很好 没学过更好
OK. I just want to phrase it as a divide-and-conquer
我把这个二分查找按分治法一步一步来
because you don't normally see it that way.
你一般看不出来这里有分治策略
The divide step is you compare x with the middle element in your array.
"分"就是把x与数组的中间元素相比较
Then the conquer step.
接下来是"治"
Here is your array. Here is the middle element.
这是一个数组 中间元素在这
You compare x with this thing
拿x和它比较
if let's say x is smaller than the middle element in your array.
假设x比中间元素小
You know that x is in the left half
那么x一定在左半边
because it is sorted,
因为数组是非递减排序的
a nice loop invariant there, whatever,
一个固定循环可以实现
but we are just going to think of that as recursively
但我们要用递归的方式来解决这个问题
I am going to solve the problem of finding x in this subarray.
我要在这个子数组中来找到x
We recurse in one subarray,
我们只在一个子数组中递归
unlike merge sort where we had two recursions.
这与归并排序有两个子问题不同
And then the combined step we don't do anything.
最后 在合并这一步没有计算量
I mean if you find x in here
只要你在这里找到x
then you've found x in the whole array.
那么在整个数组中间x就在这里
There is nothing to bring it back up really.
就没必要再合并了
So, this is just phrasing binary search as in the divide-and-conquer paradigm.
这就是二分查找算法中的分治策略
It is kind of a trivial example,
这个例子没什么意义
but there are lots of circumstances
但是有很多情况
where you only need to recurse in one side.
只需要在一边做递归
And it is important to see
而且重要的是
how much of a difference making one recursion versus making two recursions can be.
看到做一个递归与做两个递归的差别
This is the recurrence for binary search.
这是二分查找算法的递归式
We start with a problem size n.
问题的初始规模是n
We reduce it to 1.
划分后子问题只有一个
There is an implicit 1 factor here.
这省略了一个因子1
One subproblem of size n over 2.
子问题的规模是n/2
Roughly again, floors and ceilings don't matter.
上下界还是可以忽略不计
Plus a constant which is to compare x with the middle element,
x和中间元素的比较的工作是一个常量
so it is actually like one comparison.
因为只有一次比较
This has a solution, log n.
最后这个递归式等于logn
And you all know the running time of binary search,
现在你们知道二分查找的时间复杂度了
but here it is at solving the recurrence.
但递归这里
I mean, there are a couple of differences here.
这两个问题有些不同
We don't have the additive order n term.
二分查找的复杂度没有额外的n项
If we did, it would be linear, the running the time.
就算也有线性复杂度的工作量
Still better than n log n.
结果仍然比 nlogn 快
So, we are getting rid of the 2, bringing it down to a 1,
这个2在这变成了1
taking the n and bringing it down to a 1.
n在这也变成了1
That is making the running time a lot faster,
所以这个时间快很多
the whole factor of n faster.
综合起来很快
No big surprise there.
很简单
Let's do some more interesting algorithms.
再来看另外一些有意思的算法
The powering a number problem is I give you a number x.
乘方问题 给你一个数x
I give that as like a real number or floating point number or whatever.
比如一个实数或者浮点数什么的
And I give you an integer n, at least zero.
然后再给你个正整数n
I want to compute x to the power n.
叫你计算x的n次方
So, it's a very simple problem.
这个问题很简单
It is, in some sense, even easier than all of these.
比前面这些问题都简单
But here it is.
我们来看看吧
And divide-and-conquer is sort of the right thing to do.
用分治法可以解决它
So, the naive algorithm is very simple.
朴素算法非常简单
How do you compute x to the power n?
你算x的n次方是怎么算的
Well, the definition of x to the power n is
x的n次方定义是
I take x and I multiply by x n times.
把x连乘n次
So, I take x times x times x times x where there are n copies of x totally.
x乘以x乘以...n个x
And that's x to the n.
这就是x的n次方
No big surprise.
就这么简单
That is n multiplications, or n minus 1 multiplications,
需要做n或n-1次乘法
theta n time.
Θ(n)的工作量
But that's not the best you can do for this problem.
但这不是最佳的算法
Any suggestions on what we might do using divide-and-conquer?
谁能想到怎么用分治策略
Has anyone seen this algorithm before?
有人以前学过这个算法吗
A few, OK. For the rest?
有一些人 很好 那其他人呢
Testing on the spot creativity, which is very difficult,
创新很难
but I always like a challenge.
但我喜欢这样的问题
I mean random ideas.
灵感很重要
What could we possibly do to solve this problem in less than linear time?
如何在非线性时间内解决这个问题
How is this sort of a divide-and-conquer problem?
怎么运用分治法
We have two inputs, x and n. Yeah?
我们有两个输入x和n
We could try to divide on x.
我们可以对x进行划分
It seems a bit hard. It is just some number.
好像有点难 它是个数
Or, we could try to divide on n.
或者 对n划分
Any guesses?
谁有灵感
Look at x to the n over 2, very good.
x的n/2次方 非常好
That is exactly the idea of the divide-and-conquer algorithm.
这就是分治法的运用
We would like to look at x to the n over 2.
来看x的n/2次方
This is going to be a little bit tricky.
这里有点小麻烦
Now we are going to have to pay attention to floors and ceilings.
这次我们需要注意上下界
What I would like to say is
x的n次方
while x to the n is x to the n over 2
就是x的n/2次方
times x to the n over 2.
乘上x的n/2次方
And this is true if n is even.
如果n为偶数这个没问题
If it is odd then I need to be a little bit more careful.
如果n是奇数就需要注意下
But let's just think about the intuition
我们想为什么
why this is a good divide-and-conquer algorithm.
用分治法来解这个问题比较好
We have a problem of size n, let's say.
这个问题的规模是n
We convert it into, it looks like two subproblems of size n over 2,
划分后两个子问题的规模是n/2
but in fact they are the same subproblems.
而且两个子问题性质相同
So, I only have to solve one of them.
所以 只要解决一个子问题就行了
If I compute x to the n over 2.
如果已经算出x的n/2次方
Yeah, I know x to the n over 2.
已知x的n/2次方
So, there is one conversive call, problem of size n over 2,
这的问题规模变成了n/2
then I square that number.
最后求x的n/2次方的平方
And that is one computation.
只需要一次计算
So, exactly the same recurrence as binary search,
这和二分查找的递归式一样
log n time much better than n.
logn比n好很多
Cool.
这个算法很好
I also have to solve the odd case.
接下来得考虑n为奇数的情况
So, n is odd. I will look at n minus 1 over 2.
n 为奇数 那么取(n-1)/2
N minus 1 better be even.
因为(n-1)/2是偶数
And then I am missing another factor of x.
最后再乘上一个x得到最后结果
If n is odd,
如果n是偶数
I am going to have to do one recursive call and two multiplications.
需要一次递归调用和两次乘法
The same recurrence.
递归式还是一样
One recursive problem of size n over 2, plus constant time.
递归的规模是n/2然后加上常量
The dividing work here is dividing by 2
子问题的规模是n/2
and the combination work is doing one or possibly two multiplications.
最后合并这一步做一次或两次乘法
And this is lg n.
递归式最后等于lgn
And if all you are allowed to do is multiply numbers,
对于连乘问题
lg n is the best you can do.
lgn 是最快的
Good. Simple but powerful.
这是个短小精悍的算法
Whenever you want to compute a power of a number, now you know what to do.
今后你遇到乘方问题就知道怎么算了
Does anyone not know the definition of Fibonacci numbers
有人不知道斐波那契数的定义
and is willing to admit it?
并且愿意承认吗
OK, so this is a good old friend.
好 所以说这是个很有用的老朋友
I will write down the definition as just a reminder.
仅作为提醒 我会写下它的定义
And, in particular, the base cases.
尤其是它的基本情况
Fibonacci numbers, I will claim, are very important
我认为斐波那契数非常重要
because it appears throughout nature.
因为它在自然界随处可见
You look at certain fruits, you see the Fibonacci sequence.
你看到某种水果 就看到了斐波那契数列
If you count the number of little bumps around each ring.
如果你数每次铃声中的振动次数
If you look at the sand on the beach
如果你注意海滩上的沙子
and how the waves hit it,
还有海浪拍打它的方式
it's the Fibonacci sequence I am told.
这就是我所说的斐波那契数列
If you look all over the place, Fibonacci sequence is there.
如果你环视穹庐 都能找到斐波那契数列
How does nature compute the Fibonacci sequence?
那么大自然是如何计算斐波那契数列的
Well, that is a different class.
这是另外一门课了
But how are we going to compute the Fibonacci sequence as fast as possible?
但我们如何能尽快计算斐波那契数列
You have probably seen two algorithms.
你们很可能已经看过两种算法
The most naive algorithm is the recursive algorithm.
最朴素的一种算法是递归算法
Where you say OK, f of n. I say well, if n is zero, return zero,
f(n)如果当n为0返回0
if n is 1, return one.
如果n为1则返回 1
Otherwise, recursively compute
否则就递归计算
f of n minus 1 and f of n minus 2,
f(n-1)与f(n-2)
add them together.
将它们全加起来
How much time does this algorithm take,
这个算法将占用多少时间
for those who have seen it before?
有人之前考虑过吗
This is not obvious to guess.
这不是显而易见能猜出来的
It doesn't have to be exact.
这不需要精确
OK. And how many people have seen this algorithm before and analyzed it?
好吧 谁之前看到并分析过这个算法
Half, OK. So what is the running time?
一半 好的 那么运行时间是多少
Really, really long, very good.
非常非常久 非常好
Anymore precise answers? What's that?
有更精确的答案吗 有吗
Exponential, yes.
指数级 是的
That is also correct and more precise.
这也是正确的并且更精确
I will be even more precise.
我给出的将更精确
Maybe you haven't seen this analysis before.
可能你们没看到过这样的分析
It's phi to the n
这是φ的n次方
where phi is the Golden Ratio.
φ是黄金比例
Again, Golden Ratio appears throughout the world in mathematics.
黄金比例在数学的世界中无处不在
This is probably the only time in this class, I'm afraid, but there we go.
但恐怕这可能是本节课中唯一一次接触
It made its cameo so we are happy.
我们很高兴邂逅黄金分割
This is called exponential time.
这就是所谓的指数级时间
This is bigger than one, that's all you need to know.
这比1要大 你们都应该知道
This is exponential time.
这是指数级运行时间
Exponential time means basically some constant to the power n.
指数级时间意味着n的常数次方
Exponential time is a very long time.
指数级时间是很长的一段时间
It's bad. Polynomial time is good. [LAUGHTER]
这太差啦 多项式时间很好
This is what we want, polynomial time algorithms.
我们想要的就是多项式时间的算法
This class is basically entirely about polynomial time algorithms.
这节课基本上全部是关于多项式时间算法
Question?
有问题吗
Oh, say what the algorithm does again.
哦 再说一次算法做了什么
Define function Fibonacci of n?
f(n)定义了n的斐波那契函数
I check for the base cases.
我查看是不是这些基本情况
Otherwise, I recursively call Fibonacci of n minus 1.
否则 我递归调用n-1的斐波那契函数
I recursively call Fibonacci of n minus 2
递归n-2的斐波那契函数
and add those two numbers together.
并将两结果相加
So, you get this branching tree.
因此你得到了这个分支树
You are solving two subproblems of almost the same size,
你再处理两个规模几乎一致的子问题
just additively smaller by one or two.
仅仅是累计减少了1或者2的规模
I mean you are almost not reducing the problem size at all,
我的意思是这几乎没有降低问题的规模
so that's intuitively why it is exponential.
这就是为什么直觉上复杂度会是指数级
You can draw a recursion tree
你可以画一个递归树
and you will see how big it gets and how quickly.
然后你会发现它生成多大 增长多快
I mean by n over two levels,
我指的是在n/2层级上
you've only reduced on one branch the problem from n to n over 2.
在一个分支上 问题规模从n降到n/2
The other one, maybe you've gotten from n down to one,
另一分支的规模则可能因此从n降到1
but none of the branches have stopped after n of two levels.
但是没有哪个分支会在到n/2之后停止
You have at least 2 to the power n over 2
计算次数至少是2的n/2次幂
which is like square root of 2 to the power n,
也就是根号2的n次幂
which is getting close to phi to the n.
这与φ的n次方相当接近了
So, this is definitely exponential.
因此 这确实是指数级的复杂度
And exponential is bad. We want polynomial.
而指数级并不理想 我们想要多项式级
N squared, n cubed, log n would be nice.
n²、n³、logn等会比较理想
Anything that is bounded above by a polynomial is good.
任何以多项式级为上限的算法就是好算法
This is an old idea.
这是一个古老的思想
It goes back to one of the main people
它出自某位重要的人物
who said polynomial is good,
他声称多项式级很好
Jack Edmonds who is famous in the combinatorial optimization world.
他就是杰克-埃德蒙 在组合优化领域很有名
He is my academic grandfather on one side.
学术方面他算是我的祖师爷
He is a very interesting guy.
他是个非常有意思的人
OK, so that's a really bad algorithm.
好的 这确实是个糟糕的算法
You have probably seen a somewhat better algorithm,
你们很可能已经看到过一个更好的算法
which you might think of as the bottom-up implantation of that recursive algorithm.
可以认为是自下而上递归解决的算法
Or, another way to think of it is
或者 另一种理解它的思路是
if you build out the recursion tree for Fibonacci of n,
如果你建立关于n的斐波那契递归树
you will see that there are lots of common subtrees
你会发现很多公共子树
that you are just wasting time on.
而它们只会耗费你的时间
When you solve Fibonacci of n minus 1,
当你计算n-1的斐波那契函数时
it again solves Fibonacci of n minus 2.
n-2的斐波那契函数重复计算了
Why solve it twice? You only need to solve it once.
为什么要计算两次 你只需要计算一次
So, it is really easy to do that if you do it bottom-up.
如果自下而上处理 事情就变得很简单
But you could also do it recursively with some cache of things
但是你也可以通过将一些已经计算过的
you have already computed.
内容缓存的方式来递归处理
So, no big surprise.
所以 不用太惊讶
You compute the Fibonacci numbers in order.
依次计算这些斐波那契数
And each time, when you compute Fibonacci of n,
每次计算与n相关的斐波那契数项时
let's say, you have already computed the previous two,
可以说 你已经计算出了前两项
you add them together, it takes constant time.
仅将之前的两项相加 耗费的时间固定
So, the running time here is linear, linear in n,
因此运行时间是线性的 与n相关
and as our input. Great.
我们的输入也是线性的 很好
Is that the best we can do? No.
这是我们能做到的最好程度吗 不是
Any ideas on how we could compute Fibonacci of n faster than linear time?
有比这个线性时间更快的方法吗
Now we should diverge from what you have already seen, most of you.
现在要从我们已经学过的内容延伸出去
Any ideas using techniques you have already seen? Yes?
有任何想法吗 请说
Yes. We can use the mathematical trick of phi and psi to the nth powers.
是的 我们可以运用求n次幂的数学技巧
In fact, you can just use phi, phi, pi, pho, phum,
实际上你可以使用φ、ψ、π...
whatever you want to call this Greek letter.
用什么希腊字母都可以
Good. Here is the mathematical trick.
好的 这是数学技巧
And, indeed, this is cheating, as you have said.
同时 如你所说 这实际上是在作弊
This is no good, but so it is. We will call it
这不好 但是有用 我们称它为
naive recursive squaring and say well, we know recursive squaring.
朴素平方递归式 我们了解这种方法
Recursive squaring takes log n time.
平方递归占用logn这么多时间
Let's use recursive squaring.
我们来用平方递归
And if you happen to know lots of properties of the Fibonacci numbers,
而如果你碰巧了解很多斐波那契数的特性
you don't have to,
当然事实上你不必了解很多
but here is one of them.
但这里确实涉及到其中一个特性
If you take phi to the n divided by root 5
如果你用φ的n次幂去除以根号5
and you round it to the nearest integer
并取整至最接近的整数
that is the nth Fibonacci number.
那就是第n位斐波那契数
This is pretty cool. Fibonacci of n is basically phi to the n.
这很酷 Fn基本上就是φ的n次幂
We could apply recursive squaring
我们可以用平方递归在logn时间内
to compute phi to the n in log n time,
计算出φ的n次幂
divide by root 5, assume that our computer has an operation
再除以根号5 假设计算机有一项操作
that rounds a number to its nearest integer
能将一个数取整为最接近它的整数
and poof, we are done.
哦 我们搞定了
That doesn't work for many different reasons.
由于各种原因 这方法实际上不能实现
On a real machine,
在现实中的机器上
probably you would represent phi and root 5 as floating point numbers
很有可能你得用浮点数表示φ和根号5
which have some fixed amount of precise bits.
浮点数有一些固定的精确位数
And if you do this computation,
而如果你作这些运算
you will lose some of the important bits.
你将丢失一些重要的位
And when you round to the nearest integer you won't get the right answer.
而当你最近取整时你将得不到正确答案
So, floating point round off will kill you on a floating point machine.
因此浮点机上不能取四舍五入将使你功亏一篑
On a theoretical machine where we magically have numbers
假设有一台奇妙的理论机器
that can do crazy things like this,
能够实现此类疯狂的运算
I mean it really takes more than constant time per multiplication.
这里每次乘法运算确实都要超过常数时间
So, we are sort of in a different model.
因此我们采用了一种略有不同的模型
You cannot multiply phi times phi in constant time.
你不能在常数时间内完成φ乘以φ
I mean that's sort of outside the boundaries of this course,
我是指这多少超出了本课程的范围
but that's the way it is.
但事实确实如此
In fact, in a normal machine,
实际上 在一台普通机器上
some problems you can only solve in exponential time.
有些问题你只能用指数时间的算法解决
In a machine where you can multiply real numbers
而在一类理论机器上 你可以
and round them to the nearest integers,
将现实数据相乘并取最近的整数值
you can solve them in polynomial time.
你就能在多项式时间内解决问题
So, it really breaks the model.
因此这确实打破了常规模式
You can do crazy things if you were allowed to do this.
条件允许的话 你们可以试着疯狂一把
This is not allowed.
这个算法在现有条件下不能实现
And I am foreshadowing like three classes ahead,
在三节课之前我就已经预示过了
or three courses ahead, so I shouldn't talk more about it.
或者三门课程之前 因此我不想再多谈
But it turns out we can use recursive squaring in a different way
但如果运用斐波那契数的另一种特性
if we use a different property of Fibonacci numbers.
就可以用另一种方式来使用平方递归
And then we will just stick with integers and everything will be happy.
接下来的算法只有整数 所以问题很好解决
Don't forget to go to recitation and if you want to homework lab.
别忘了参加复习课 大家可以去实验室
Don't come here on Monday. That is required.
周一别来这了 这是要求
This is sort of the right recursive squaring algorithm.
某种程度上这才是真正的平方递归算法
And this is a bit hard to guess if you haven't already seen it,
如果你没见过这算法 要猜出来有点难
so I will just give it to you.
所以我会把这个算法给你们
turns out ...I will call this a theorem.
显然... 我把这称为定理
It's the first time I get to use the word theorem in this class.
这是我这节课上第一次用“定理”这个词
It turns out the nth Fibonacci number is the nth power of this matrix.
第n个斐波那契数就是这个矩阵的n次幂
Cool. If you look at it a little bit you say oh, yeah, of course.
如果多看几眼你会说 哦是的 当然
And we will prove this theorem in a second.
一会我们就会证明这个定理
But once we have this theorem,
但是一旦我们有了这个定理
we can compute f of n by computing the nth power of this matrix.
我们可以通过计算矩阵的n次幂来得到Fn
It's a two-by-two matrix.
这是一个二阶矩阵
You multiply two two-by-two matrixes together,
你将两个二阶矩阵相乘
you get a two-by-two matrix.
得到一个二阶矩阵
So that is constant size, four numbers.
所以那是常数规模 只有四个数
I can handle four numbers.
我能处理四个数
We don't have crazy precision problems on the floating point side.
就不必面对浮点机令人发狂的精确度问题
There are only four numbers to deal with.
只需要处理四个数
Matrixes aren't getting bigger.
矩阵不会变大
So, the running time of this divide-and-conquer algorithm
所以分治算法的运行时间
will still be log n
始终保持为logn
because it takes a constant time per two-by-two matrix multiplication. Yes?
因为二阶矩阵相乘占用常数时间 什么
Oh, yes. Thank you. I have a type error.
哦 是的 谢谢 我有个笔误
Sorry about that. F of n is indeed the upper left corner, I hope.
很抱歉 我想Fn确实应该是在左上角
I better check I don't have it off by one. I do.
检查下有没有漏了减1 确实漏了
It's F_n upper right corner, indeed. That's what you said.
像你说的 Fn确实应该在右上角
F of n. I need more space. Sorry.
Fn 我需要更多空间 不好意思
I really ought to have a two-by-two matrix on the left-hand side there.
我真的应该将二阶矩阵写在左手边上
Thank you.
谢谢
So, I compute this nth power of a matrix in log n time,
那么 在logn时间内计算矩阵的n次幂
I take the upper right corner or the lower left corner, your choice,
从右上角或者左下角开始 都可以
that is the nth Fibonacci number.
结果就得到第n个斐波那契数
This implies an order log n time algorithm
这就是logn时间的算法
with the same recurrence as the last two,
与前面提到的两个算法递归程度相同
binary search and really the recursive squaring algorithm.
也就是二分查找和刚才的平方递归算法
It is log n plus a constant, so log n.
logn加上一个常数 还是logn
Let's prove that theorem.
现在来证明这个定理
Any suggestions on what techniques we might use for proving this theorem,
有哪些方法可以用呢 有什么建议吗
or what technique, singular?
或者什么技巧
Induction, very good.
归纳法 很好
I think any time I ask that question the answer is induction.
任何时候我问这个问题 答案都是归纳法
Hint for the future in this class.
一个提示 以后的课上都会有用
A friend of mine,
我的一个朋友
when he took an analysis class, whenever the professor asked,
当他在上分析课时 每当教授问到
and what is the answer to this question, the answer was always zero.
这个问题的答案是什么 答案总是0
If you have taken analysis class that is funny. [LAUGHTER]
如果你们上分析课 就会发现这很有趣
Maybe I will try to ask some questions
我也许应该提一些答案为0的
whose answers are zero just for our own amusement.
问题 仅供我们自娱自乐
We are going to induct on n. It's pretty much the obvious thing to do.
接下来就是对n归纳 这是显而易见的
But we have to check some cases.
但是我们还要先检查一些特殊情况
So, the base case is we have this to the first power.
基本情况就是将之应用到一次幂
And that is itself [(1, 1), (1, 0)].
而结果就是它本身[(1, 1), (1, 0)]
And I should have said n is at least 1.
另外应当规定n至少为1
And you can check.
你们可以检查下
This is supposed to be F_2, F_1, F_1, F_0.
这应当是F₂ F₁ F₁ F₀
And you can check it is, F_0 is 0, F_1 is 1 and F_2 is 1. Good.
而F₀是0 F₁是1 F₂是1 很好
Base case is correct, step case is about as exciting,
基本情况成立 下面就可以递推了
but you've got to prove that your algorithm works.
但你必须证明你的算法有效
Suppose this is what we want to compute.
假设这是我们要计算的
I am just going to sort of, well, there are many ways I can do this.
有用的方法 某种程度上来说有很多种
I will just do it the fast way because it's really not that exciting.
鉴于这并非高潮 我会单刀直入地解决
Which direction? Let's do this direction.
哪个方向 就这个方向吧
I want to use induction on n.
我想对n进行归纳
If I want to use induction on n,
那么 如果我要对n进行归纳
presumably I should use what I already know is true.
理论上来说我应该可以用已知正确的东西
If I decrease n by 1, I have this property
如果将n减1 就有这样的特性
that this thing is going to be [(1, 1), (1, 0)] to the power n minus 1.
这个就等于[(1, 1), (1, 0)]的n-1次幂
This I already know, by the induction hypothesis,
根据归纳假设 我已经知道这点了
[(1, 1), (1, 0)] to the n minus 1.
[(1, 1), (1, 0)]的n-1次幂
So, presumably I should use it in some way.
因此我估计我应当在某个地方用到这个
This equality is not yet true, you may have noticed.
你们也许注意到了 这个等式还不成立
So, I need to add something on.
因此我需要加上一些东西
What could I possibly add on to be correct?
加上什么才能保证等式会成立呢
Well, another factor of [(1, 1), (1, 0)].
另一个已知的项[(1, 1), (1, 0)]
The way I am developing this proof is the only way it could possibly be,
到目前为止的推导步骤是我们唯一能做的
in some sense.
某种程度上来说是这样
If you know its induction, this is all that you could do.
如果你了解归纳法 这是你能做的全部
And then you check. Indeed, this equality holds conveniently.
检查一下 事实上这个等式其实很简单
For example, F_(n plus 1) is the product of these two things.
例如 F(n+1)是这两个乘积
It is this row times this column.
行乘以列
So, it is F_n times 1 plus F_(n minus 1) times 1,
所以这就是Fn乘以1加上F(n-1)乘以1
which is indeed the definition of F_(n plus 1).
而这实际上就是F(n+1)的定义
And you could check four of the entries.
然后你可以检查这四个数
This is true. Great.
正确 太棒了
If that is true then I would just put these together.
既然这是对的 接下来我就都放到一起
That is [(1, 1), (1, 0)] to the n minus 1
那就是[(1, 1), (1, 0)]的n-1次幂
times [(1, 1), (1, 0)],
乘以[(1, 1), (1, 0)]
which is [(1, 1), (1, 0)] to the n, end of proof.
得到[(1, 1), (1, 0)]的n次幂 结束
A very simple proof,
非常简单的证明过程
but you have to do that in order to know if this algorithm really works.
但你必须按部就班以确保你的算法有效
Good. Question?
很好 有问题吗
Oh, yes. Thank you.
哦是的 谢谢
This, in the lower right, we should have F_(n minus 1).
这里 右下角 应该是F(n-1)
This is why you should really check your proofs.
这就是为什么你们应当检查自己的证明
We would have discovered that
在我检查行乘以列的时候
when I checked that this was that row times that column,
就应该发现这个问题
but that is why you are here, to fix my bugs.
但这就是你们在这里的原因 挑我的错
That's the great thing about being up here instead of in a quiz.
现在就发现 总比在测验中发现要好
But that is a minor mistake.
当然这只是一个小错误
You wouldn't lose much for that.
你不会为此付出太大代价
All right. More divide-and-conquer algorithms.
好的 现在我们要进一步探讨分治算法
Still, we have done relatively simple ones so far.
目前为止我们完成了一些相对简单的例子
In fact, the fanciest has been merge sort, which we already saw.
实际上 时间效率最好的是归并排序
So, that is not too exciting.
因此 这些就显得不那么令人兴奋了
The rest have all be log n time.
因为它们都是logn时间的
Let's break out of the log n world.
让我们离开logn的世界
Well, you all have the master method memorized, right,
现在你们都记住了主方法 是吗
so I can erase that.
所以我现在把这些都擦掉了
Good. This will be a good test.
好的 接下来将是一个很棒的测试
Next problem is matrix multiplication,
下一个问题是矩阵乘法
following right up on this two-by-two matrix multiplication.
紧跟着这个2×2矩阵乘法
Let's see how we can compute n-by-n matrix multiplications.
让我们看看如何进行n×n矩阵乘法
Just for a recap, you should know how to multiply matrixes,
简单提一下 你们应当了解矩阵乘法
but here is the definition, so we can turn it into an algorithm.
但这里矩阵乘法的定义将被当做算法问题
You have two matrixes, A and B, which are capital levels.
有两个矩阵 A和B 大写字母表示
The ijth entry. Ith row, jth column is called little aij
第ij项 第i行 第j列称为aij
or little bij.
或者bij
And your goal is to compute the products of those matrixes.
我们的目标是计算矩阵的乘积
I should probably say that i and j range from 1 to n.
i和j的范围都是1到n
So, they are square matrixes.
因此它们是方阵
The output is to compute C
输出矩阵用字母C表示
which has entry cij which is the product of A and B.
它的每一项cij是A和B的对应乘积
And, for a recap, the ijth entry of the product is
简单回顾一下 乘积的第ij项是
the inner product of the ith row of A with the jth column of B.
A的第i行与B的第j列的内积
But you can write that out as a sum like so.
但是你也可以写成这样的求和形式
We want to compute this thing for every i and j.
我们希望对每个i和j进行这样的计算
What is the obvious algorithm for doing this?
这个问题最明显的算法是怎样的呢
Well, for every i and j you compute the sum.
当然是对每个i和j分别求和
You compute all the products.
分别计算出所有的乘积
You compute the sum.
然后求和
So, it's like n operations here roughly.
那么 这样看起来需要n步操作
I mean like 2n minus 1, whatever.
大概2n-1步操作吧
It is order n operations.
这是线性阶的操作
There are n² entries of C that I need to compute,
矩阵C共有n²项需要计算
so that's n³ time.
因此一共需要n³时间
I will write this out just for the programmers at heart.
我把这个算法写下来 你们可以记一下
Here is the pseudocode.
伪代码如下
It's rare that I will write pseudocode.
我很少会把伪代码写下来
And this is a simple enough algorithm that I can write it in gory detail.
这个算法很简单 我可以详细地写出来
But it gives you some basis for this analysis if you like to program.
但如果你想编程 程序结构也是这样
It is a triply nested for loop.
这是一个三层for循环
And I made a coding error.
看起来我犯了一个代码上的错误
Hopefully you haven't written that far yet.
希望你们还没有记到这里
I need cij to be initialized to zero.
我需要把cij初始化为0
And then I add to cij the appropriate product, a_ik, b_kj.
然后把对应的aik与bkj的乘积加到cij
That is the algorithm.
这就是这个算法
And the point is you have a nesting of n for loops
关键是 这里需要嵌套的for循环
from 1 to n. That takes n³ time
从1循环到n 这将花费n³时间
because this is constant and that is constant.
因为这和这是常数时间
So, very simple, n³. Let's do better.
很简单 n³ 现在来做点改进
And, of course, we are going to use divide-and-conquer.
当然 我们将要采用分治法
Now, how are we going to divide a matrix?
现在 我们将如何分割一个矩阵呢
There are a lot of numbers in a matrix, n² of them in each one.
矩阵里有很多数字 每个矩阵有n²个
There are all sorts of ways you could divide.
你有各种方式来分割
So far all of the divide-and-conquers
目前为止所有的分治问题
we have done have been problems of size n into
我们都是把规模为n的问题
some number of problems of size n over 2.
分割成规模为n/2的两部分
I am going to say I start with some matrixes of size n-by-n.
那么让我们考虑某个n×n的矩阵
I want to convert it down to something like n/2-by-n/2.
我希望将它转化为n/2乘n/2规模
Any suggestions how I might do that?
我该怎么做呢 有没有什么建议
Yeah? Block form the matrix, indeed.
对 确实 矩阵分块
That is the right answer.
就是这样
So, this is the first divide-and-conquer algorithm.
所以 这将是第一个分治算法
This will not work, but it has the first idea that we need.
还没有用 但这是我们首先需要的思想
We have a n-by-n matrix.
我们有一个n×n的矩阵
We can view it, this equality is more, you can think of it as,
我们可以这样看待它 你可以把它当作
it's really the thing, a two-by-two block matrix
2×2的块矩阵 这才是真正需要的
where each entry in this two-by-two block matrix
这个块矩阵的每个元素
is a block of n/2-by-n/2 submatrixes.
都是规模为n/2乘n/2的子矩阵块
I will think of C as being divided into three parts, r, s, t and u.
考虑C被分为四个部分 r, s, t和u
Even though I write them as lower case letters they are really matrixes.
我使用了小写字母 但实际都表示矩阵
Each is n/2-by-n/2.
每个都是n/2乘n/2
And A, I will split into a, b, c, d,
然后矩阵A 划分为a,b,c,d
times B, I will split into e, f, g, h.
乘以矩阵B 划分为e,f,g,h
Why not? This is certainly true.
为什么不呢 这当然是正确的
And if you've seen some linear algebra,
只要你学过一点线性代数就会知道
this is basically what you can do with matrixes.
这是基本的矩阵操作
Now I can pretend these are two-by-two and sort of forget the fact
现在我们可以假装这些矩阵是2×2的
that these little letters are matrixes and say well,
假装忘记这些小写字母也是矩阵的事实
r is the inner product of this row with this column.
r是这一行和这一列的内积
It is ae times bg.
是ae+bg
Let me not cheat or else it will be too easy.
我把这些都写一下吧 很简单
r=ae+bg, s=af+bh, t=ce+dg and u=cf+dh.
r=ae+bg, s=af+bh, t=ce+dg以及u=cf+dh
It's nothing like making it too hard on yourself.
你们自己做也并不难
OK, got them right. Good.
没错吧 很好
I mean this is just a fact about how you would expand out this product.
所以 这是事实上展开这个乘积的方法
And so now we have a recursive algorithm.
因此现在我们有了一个递归的算法
In fact, we have a divide-and-conquer algorithm.
事实上 是一个分治的算法
We start with our n-by-n matrix.
我们由n×n矩阵开始
Well, we have two of them actually.
嗯 事实上我们有两个这样的矩阵
We divide it into eight little pieces, a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h.
我们将它们分8块: a,b,c,d,e,f,g,h
Then we compute these things and that gives us C,
然后计算这些 得到C
just by sticking them together.
只要把它们组合到一起就可以了
Now, how do we compute these things?
现在 我们怎样来计算这些呢
Well, these innocent-looking little products
嗯 这些看上去很无辜的乘积
between these two little numbers
也就是这两个小小的数的乘积
are actually recursive matrix multiplications.
事实上是递归的矩阵乘法
Because each of these little letters is an n/2-by-n/2 matrix
因为这些字母实际上都是n/2乘n/2的矩阵
so I have to recursively compute the product.
因此我们需要递归地计算乘积
There are like eight recursive multiplications of n/2-by-n/2 matrixes.
看起来需要8次n/2乘n/2矩阵的递归乘积
That is what bites us.
这看起来可不太妙
And then there are like four additions,
然后 貌似还需要4次矩阵求和
plus minor work of gluing things together.
加上把各部分合并的一些简单操作
How long does it take to add two matrixes together?
两个矩阵相加需要多长时间呢
n². This is cheap.
n的平方 代价很低
It just takes n².
只需要n的平方
Remember, we are trying to beat n³ for our matrix multiplication.
我们想把总时间复杂度降到n³以下
Addition is a really easy problem.
加法是一个多么简单的问题
You just have to add every number.
只需要对所有数字简单地相加
There is no way you can do better than n².
没有办法做到比n平方更好
So, that is not recursive. That is the nice thing.
因此它不是递归的 这一点很好
But the bad thing is we have eight of these recursions.
但是讨厌的是需要8次这样的递归
And I have erased the master method, but you should all have it memorized.
我把主方法擦掉了 但是你们应该记得
What is the solution to this recurrence?
对于这样的递推该怎么办呢
All right. A is 8, b is 2, log base 2 of 8 is 3.
a是8 b是2 以2为底的8的对数是3
Every computer scientist should know that.
每个计算机科学家都要知道这个
That is polynomially larger than n²,
这个多项式的阶数比平方高
so we are in Case 1.
因此符合主方法第一种情况
Thank you. Let's get them upside down.
谢谢 写在下面
This is n³, no better than our previous algorithm.
结果是n立方 并不比先前的算法优秀
That kind of sucks.
毫无用处
And now comes the divine inspiration. Let's go over here.
现在回到最初分治的灵感上来
There are some algorithms like this Fibonacci algorithm
考虑某种类似于斐波那契数的算法
where if you sat down for a little while,
你只要坐下来略加思考
it's no big deal, you would figure it out.
就可以解决 这个问题不难
I mean it is kind of clever to look at that matrix
我们用一种更巧妙的方式来观察这个矩阵
and then everything works happily.
然后问题就可以轻易解决了
It is not obvious but it is not that amazingly clever.
这个方法不容易想到 但却惊人地巧妙
This is an algorithm that is amazingly clever.
这是一个特别巧妙的算法
You may have seen it before which steals the thunder a little bit,
你可能之前已经看过了
but it is still really, really cool so you should be happy to see it again.
但是这个算法真的很酷 值得你再看看
And how Strassen came up with this algorithm,
那么斯特拉森是如何想出这个算法的呢
he must have been very clever.
他一定非常聪明
The idea is we've got to get rid of these multiplications.
关键思路是 我们得绕过这些乘法
I don't really care. I could do a hundred additions.
我并不介意多做几百次加法
I have to reduce this 8 to something smaller. It turns out,
关键是我需要把这里的8变小 事实上
if you try to split the matrices into three-by-three or something,
如果你尝试把矩阵分为3×3甚至更多块
that doesn't help you.
并不会带来任何帮助
You get the same problem
你会遇到同样的问题
because we're using fundamentally the same algorithm,
因为我们在使用同样的算法
just in a different order.
仅仅变化了顺序
We have got to somehow reduce the number of multiplications.
我们需要想办法减少乘法的次数
We are going to reduce it to 7.
把它减少到7
The claim is that if we have two two-by-two matrices
这就意味着 如果我们有两个2×2矩阵
we can take their product using seven multiplications.
我们可以只通过七次乘法得到它们的乘积
If that were true,
如果真的可以这样的话
we would reduce the 8 to a 7 and presumably make things run faster.
这里的8就减少到了7 运行会快一些
We will see how fast in a moment.
等一下我们来看看具体有多快
You can compute it in your head.
你可以心算一下
If you are bored and like computing logs
如果你百无聊赖而且喜欢计算对数的话
that are non-integral logs then go ahead.
那些是非整数的对数 好吧随便你
All right. Here we are.
好的 我们刚才讲到这里
This algorithm is unfortunately rather long,
很不幸这个算法很长
but it is only seven multiplications.
但是却只有七次乘法
Each of these P's is a product of two things
每个P都是两项相乘的结果
which only involves addition or subtraction, the same thing.
每一项只涉及加减法 它们的复杂度是一样的
Those are seven multiplications.
一共有7次乘法
And I can compute those in 7T(n/2).
我们可以在7T(n/2)时间内完成
Oh, indeed it is. Six was wrong.
哦 事实上第六个写错了
Six and seven are the same, very good.
第六个写成和第七个一样了 很好
You know, you think that
要知道
copying something would not be such a challenging task.
复制粘贴并不是什么很有挑战性的工作
But when you become an absent-minded professor like me
但如果你也成了一个像我一样走神的教授
then you will know how easy it is.
你就会知道这到底是难还是简单啦
OK. We have them all correct, hopefully.
好 但愿我们都写对了
We continue. That wasn't enough.
继续 还没完
Of course we had seven things.
当然我们有了7个结果
Clearly we have to reduce this down to four things,
明显我们还需要把它们搞成四项
the elements of C.
C的元素
Here they are, the elements of C, r, s, t, u.
它们在这里 C的元素r s t u
It turns out r=P5+P4-P2+P6.
事实上r=P₅+P₄-P₂+P₆
Of course. Didn't you all see that?
当然 你们都看到了吧
I mean this one is really easy, s=P1+P2.
这个很简单 s=P₁+P₂
I mean that is clearly how they were chosen.
明显它们就是因为这个才被选为这样的
And then u is another tricky one,
u也有点技巧性
OK. Now, which one of these would you like me to check?
好了 现在你们希望我检查哪一个
Don't be so nice. How about s?
心眼别太坏 s怎么样
I can show you s is right.
我可以秀给你们
Any preferences? u. Oh, no, sign errors.
选哪个 u 哦 想看有没有符号错误
OK. Here we go.
很好
The claim that this really works is
你要检查过所有四个后
you have to check all four of them.
才能认为这个算法确实可行
And I did in my notes.
我在讲义中做了
That is P_5. Check me.
那是P₅ 帮我核对下
If I screw up, I am really hosed.
如果我搞乱了那麻烦了
(af - ah)=P1.
af-ah是P₁
P3 has a minus sign in front, so that is (ce + de).
P₃前面有负号 是(ce+de)
And then we have minus P_7,
然后是负的P₇
which is a big one, (ae+af-ce-cf).
很长一串 (ae+af-ce-cf)
OK. Now I need like the assistant
现在我需要
that crosses off things in parallel like the movie, right?
去掉相同的数 像放电影样
and hopefully these survive, dh minus minus cf.
还好这两个幸存下来 dh减负的cf
And, if we are lucky, that is exactly what is written here,
如果我们幸运的话 这和写在这的一样
except in the opposite order.
只是顺序不一样
Magic, right? Where the hell did Strassen get this?
很神奇吧 斯特拉森是怎么想出来的
You have to be careful.
值得注意的是
It is OK that the plus is in the wrong order because plus is commutative,
加法无所谓顺序反了因为加法是可交换的
but the multiplications better not be in the wrong order
但是乘法可最好别反了
because multiplication over matrixes is not commutative.
因为矩阵乘法可不是可交换的
I check cf, OK, dh, they are in the right order.
检查一下cf dh 它们的顺序是对的
I won't check the other three.
我就不检查剩下三个了
That is matrix multiplication in hopefully subcubic time.
这就是小于立方级的矩阵乘法
Let's write down the recurrence.
让我们写一下递推关系
T(n) is now 7.
T(n)现在是7
Maybe I should write down the algorithm for kicks.
可能我应该把这个算法写下来
Why not? Assuming I have time.
为什么不呢 如果我有时间的话
Lots of time. Last lecture I was ten minutes early.
时间很宽裕 上节课我早了十分钟
I apologize for that. I know it really upsets you.
我为此道歉 我知道那让你们很无奈
I ended ten minutes early.
提前十分钟结束
And I didn't realize exactly when the class was supposed to end.
我并不知道课该上到什么时候结束
So, today, I get to go ten minutes late.
所以今天我要晚下课十分钟
OK. Good. I'm glad you all agree.
很好 我很高兴你们都同意
I am kidding. Don't worry. OK.
开玩笑的啦 别紧张
Algorithm. This is Strassen.
这就是今天介绍的算法 斯特拉森算法
First we divide, then we conquer and then we combine.
首先我们"分" 然后"治" 然后合并
As usual, I don't have it written anywhere here. Fine.
和以前一样 我没有在别处写过 很好
Divide A and B. This is sort of trivial.
划分A和B 这个很平常
Then we compute the terms -- -- for the products.
然后我们计算一些乘积
This means we get ready to compute all the P's.
这意味着我们要计算所有的P
We compute a+b, c+d, g-e, a+d, e+h and so on.
a+b c+d g-e a+d e+h等等
All of the terms that appear in here, we compute those.
所有的项都在这儿 我们计算一下
That takes n2 time
需要花费n平方的时间
because it is just a bunch of additions and subtractions.
因为这只需要一些加减法
No big deal. A constant number of them.
很简单 常数次运算
Then we conquer by recursively computing all the Pi's.
然后我们分别递归地处理所有的Pi
That is each our product of seven of them.
得到七个乘积
We have P1, P2 up to P7
P₁ P₂一直到P₇
And, finally, we combine, which is to compute r, s, t and u.
最后把这些组合起来计算r,s,t,u
And those are just additions and subtractions again,
现在也是些加减法运算
so they take n² times.
总共需要n²次计算
So, here we finally get an algorithm
这就是整个算法
that is nontrivial both in dividing and in combining.
这个算法在拆分和组合上面都不简单
Recursion is always recursion,
不过递归还是递归
but now we have interesting steps one and three.
只是我们现在对第一步和第三步感兴趣
The recurrence T(n) is seven recursive subproblems,
递归式T(n)包含了7个递归的子问题
each are size n/2
每个子问题规模是n/2
plus order n²,
再加上n²规模的计算
to do all this addition work.
来完成所有额外的运算
Now we need to solve this recurrence.
现在来算一下这个递归式子
We compute n^logb(a),
先计算一下n^logb(a)
which here is nlog2(7).
在这里这项是nlog2(7)
And we know log base 2 of 8 is 3.
因为以2为底8的对数是3
Log base 2 of 7 is going be a little bit less than 3
那么log2(7)应该比3小一点
but still bigger than 2
但肯定是比2大的
because log base 2 of 4 is 2.
因为以2为底4的对数才是2
So, it is going to be polynomially larger than n²
所以它应该多项式地比n²大
but polynomially smaller than n³.
但是要比n的立方小
We are again in Case 1.
所以说这个属于第一种情形
And this is the cheating way
这里我简写一下
to write n log base 2 of 7, nlg7.
以2为底7的对数写成n^lg7
lg means log base 2.
这里lg就是代表以2为底的对数
You should know that.
你要知道这个
It is all over the textbook and in our problem sets and what not, nlg7.
这种情况贯穿我们整个教材和作业
And, in particular, if I have my calculator here.
我们用计算器具体计算下
This is a good old-fashion calculator.
这个老式计算器还是很有效
No, that is wrong. Sorry.
不好意思写错了
It is strictly less than 2.81.
这个严格小于2.81
That is cool.
太棒了
I mean it is polynomially better than n³.
说明这个多项式要比3次方的算法好
Still not as good as addition, which is n².
但还是没有n²的加法运算好
It is generally believed,
我们一般认为达不到n²算法
although we don't know whether you can multiply as fast as
因为我们不知道矩阵对于乘法和除法运算
you can divide for matrices.
速度是不是一样的
We think you cannot get n², but who knows?
不过 这也说不定
It could still happen. There are no lower bounds.
它也可能发生 这里没有下限
This is not the best algorithm for matrix multiplication.
这个不是矩阵相乘最好的算法
It is sort of the simplest that beats n³.
不过这个是比n³好的最简单的算法
The best so far is like n^2.376.
目前最好的大约是n^2.376
Getting closer to 2.
正在向2进军
You might think these numbers are a bit weird.
可能会觉得这些数有点儿怪
Maybe the constants out here dominate the improvement
这里面的优化掌控在
you are getting in the exponent.
常数上面
It turns out improving the exponent is a big deal.
看起来优化了指数部分没什么
I mean, as n gets larger exponents really come out to bite you.
但是当n变大的时候 指数部分影响很吓人
So, n³ is pretty impractical for any very large values of n.
对于很大的n来说n³算法就很不切实际
And we known that Strassen will beat normal matrix multiplication
当n足够大时
if n is sufficiently large.
斯特拉森算法比普通矩阵乘法好
The claim is that roughly at about 32 or so already you get an improvement,
大概32左右就能看出差别了
for other reasons,
还有一些原因
not just because the exponent gets better, but there you go.
不仅是指数变小了 不过先就这样吧
So, this is pretty good.
确实不错
This is completely impractical, so don't use whatever this algorithm is.
这个算法完全不切实际 别用这个
I don't have the reference handy,
我这里也没相关资料
but it is just trying to get a theoretical improvement.
这个纯粹是理论上的改进
There may be others that are in between and more reasonable
可能还有更切实际一点儿的
but that is not it.
但肯定不是这个
Wow, lots of time. Any questions?
时间还很多 有问题没
We're not done yet,
现在还没完
but any questions before we move on for matrix multiplication?
关于矩阵乘法还有问题么
OK. I have one more problem.
好吧 下一个问题
Divide-and-conquer is a pretty general idea.
分治法的思想很普遍
I mean, you can use it to dominate countries.
我意思是治理国家可以用它
You can use it to multiply matrices.
矩阵相乘也可以用它
I mean, who would have thought?
谁来想一下
Here is a very different kind of problem
这有一个不同类型的问题
you can solve with divide-and-conquer.
你可以分治法思想解决
It is not exactly an algorithmic problem,
虽然跟计算机有关
although it is computer science.
不过不是严格的算法问题
That is clear. This is very large-scale integration.
这个是超大规模集成电路(VLSI)
The chips, they are very large scale integrated.
超大规模的集成的芯片
Probably even more these days, but that is the catch phrase.
可能会更大规模 不过现在是这个叫法
Here is a problem, and it arises in VLSI layout.
在集成电路布局时候显现出来一个问题
We won't get into too many details why,
我们不用考虑太细节
but you have some circuit.
现在就有一些电路
And here I am going to assume that the circuit is a binary tree.
这里我假设电路是个二叉树
This is just part of a circuit.
这个就是电路一部分
Assume for now here that it is just a complete binary tree.
假设现在这里有一个完全二叉树
A complete binary tree looks like this.
完全二叉树长这个样子
In all of my teachings,
在我教学生涯里
I have drawn this figure for sure the most.
我画这个图的次数最多
It is my favorite figure,
这是我最喜欢的图
the height four complete binary tree.
四层高的完全二叉树
OK, there it is. I have some tree like that as some height.
就是这个 还有一些一样高的树
I want to imbed it into some chip layout on a grid.
我想在网格上 把它放到芯片布局上
Let's say it has n leaves.
这个是有n个叶节点
I want to imbed it into a grid with minimum area.
我想在网格上占据最小空间
This is a very cute problem
这个问题很有意思
and it really shows you another way in
让你从另一个角度感受到
which divide-and-conquer is a useful and powerful tool.
分治这个强大而有效的工具
So, I have this tree. I like to draw it in this way.
现在这棵树我想这么画
I want to somehow draw it on the grid.
我想在网格上画出来
What that means is the vertices have to be imbedded onto dots on the grid,
就是说顶点是要放在网格上的点的
and I am talking about the square grid.
现在说的都是正方形网格
It has to go to vertices of the grid.
放在网格顶点上面去
And these edges have to be routed as sort of orthogonal paths
这些边组织成为正交路线
between one dot and another,
在点和点之间
so that should be an edge and they shouldn't cross
有一条边而且不能交叉
and all these good things because wires do not like to cross.
这么多限制 都是因为线不能交叉
There is the obvious way to solve this problem and there is the right way.
现在有一个明显的解决方案 还有一个正确的
And let's talk about both of them.
两个我都要讲
Neither of them is particularly obvious,
两个方法都不是很显然
but divide-and-conquer sort of gives you a hint in the right direction.
不过分治法思想给你一个正确的提示
So, the naive embedding. I seem to like the word naive here.
朴素算法 我现在就用朴素的算法做下
I am going to draw this bottom up because it is easier,
我准备从下往上画 这样简单点儿
so leave three grid lines and then start drawing.
留出来3排网格然后开始画
I don't know how big that is going to be.
我可不知道这得变多大
Here is the bottom of our tree.
这里是我们树的底部
This is like the little three nodes there.
看起来像是三个节点
And then I leave a blank column and then a blank column.
现在空出一个空白列 又一个
I don't actually need to leave those blank columns,
我实际上不需要留出空白列
but it makes a prettier drawing.
不过好看点儿
And then we work our way up.
继续向上
There is the tree, which should be aligned, on a grid.
就是这个树 这里对齐在网格上
No crossings. Everything is happy.
没有交叉 都很好
How much area does it take?
不过要占多大面积呢
By area, I mean sort of the area of the bounding box.
面积 我意思是说包围的方形面积
So, I count this blank space even though I am not using it
虽然空白没用上 但还是要算进去
and I count all this blank space even though I am not using it.
所有空白都要算 虽然没用上
I want to look at the height.
先看一下高度
Let's call this H(n).
记作H(n)
And to look at the width, which I will call W(n).
然后看一下宽度 记作W(n)
Now, it is probably pretty obvious that H(n) is like log n,
很显然 H(n)是logn级别
W(n) is like n or whatever.
W(n)差不多是n级别
But I want to write it as a recurrence
不过我要写成递归式
because that will inspire us to do the right thing.
因为有可能可以启发我们一下
H(n). Well, if you think of this as a recursion-tree, in some sense.
H(n) 我们把这个理解为递归树
We start with the big tree.
我们从这个大树开始
We split it into two halves,
分成两个部分
two subtrees of size n/2 indeed
这两个子树大小n/2
because we are counting leaves.
因为我们会算上叶节点
It is exactly n/2 on each side.
每一面都是n/2
Then for height they are in parallel so it is no big deal.
对于高度 它们是平行的没什么说的
The height is just the height of this thing,
高度就是这个的高度
one of these subproblems plus one.
每个子问题加一
The width, you have to add together the two widths and also add on 1.
宽度 需要加在一块然后再加1
You don't have to add on 1 here, but it doesn't matter.
这里不用加1 不过没什么关系
It is certainly at most 1.
最多是1
there you do have to add 1,
这儿再加1
The usual base cases.
常见的基本情况
I mean, these are recurrences we should know and love.
这个递归式我们知道而且喜欢
This is log n, I sort of have already given away the answers,
这个是lgn 这个解答已经差不多了
and this better be linear.
这个是线性
This is again Case 1.
这个是第一情况
And to the log base 2 of 2 is n, which is the answer, much bigger than 1.
n^log2(2)=n 这个答案比1大
And here n to the log base 2 of 1 is n to the zero,
这里n的lg1次方即n的0次方
which is 1, which is the same so we get log n.
等于1 所以得到lgn
The area is n log n,
面积是nlgn
but if you are making chips you want the area as small as possible
不过做芯片面积越小越好
so you can fit more good stuff in there.
这样就能放更多的元件
So, we would like to aim for, well,
我们想找一下
we certainly cannot do a better area than n.
不过可以肯定不会有比n更好的
You've got to put the leaves down somewhere,
现在是把叶节点放在下面
but this is already pretty good.
已经看起来不错了
It is only a log factor off, but we want to aim for n.
只过是nlgn级别的 不过我们想要n
How could we get n?
不过怎么能到n呢
Any guesses on what needs to change in this layout?
关于改变布局有没有什么猜测
Not how to do it because that is not obvious,
先不说怎么弄 这个不是那么显然
but in terms of height and width what should we do?
高度和宽度我们应该从哪入手
It is pretty hard to get the height smaller than log n,
让高度变得比lgn小看起来很困难
I will tell you, because this is a tree.
因为这是棵树
It cannot really get its width down to less than log n.
不可能让高度比lgn还小
What could we do to make the product linear?
那我们怎么才能让乘积呈线性呢
Just random ideas. What are two functions whose product is n?
发散思维 什么样的两个函数乘积是n
Square root of n and square root of n.
n的平方根和n的平方根
That is a good choice. Were there other suggestions?
不错 还有别的么
n times constant. Yeah, n times constant would be nice.
n乘以常数 对 n乘常数也不错
But I claim you cannot get either of these down to less than a constant.
不过我刚才说了 这两个没法变常数
You could aim for n over log n by log n, that is more likely,
应该关注n/lgn和lgn 这个更像一些
but I think that is almost impossible.
不过这个不可能的
Root n by root n is the right answer, so let's go with that.
n平方根乘n平方根是正确答案 我们来看一下
So, root n by root n.
n平方根乘n平方根
We haven't seen any recurrences whose solution is root n,
我们还没见过解是n平方根的递归式子呢
but surely they are out there.
不过这个就是
If we did that we would be happy,
如果能做到那就很开心了
because then the area is the product is linear.
那样的话乘积 也就是面积 是线性的
How? What is a recurrence that is in the usual master method
怎么办 主方法中哪种递归式拥有这样的形式
form whose solution is root n?
然后解是n的平方根
I mean, you could think of it that way.
我意思是可以按这种方式思考
Recurrence is a bit tricky,
这个递归式有些微妙
but let's just think of n^logb(a).
想一下n^logb(a)
When is log base b of a ? Because then n^log_b(a) is root n.
什么时候n^logb(a)是根号n
And there is some hope that I could get a root n solution to recurrence.
希望能够得到一个解是n平方根的递归式
This is designed by knowing that it is divide-and-conquer,
这个是通过分治法思想进行设计
and therefore it must be something like this.
肯定会有类似这种样子的形式
It is easy once you know
你知道了以后很简单
the approach you are supposed to take and you can try this approach.
先假设一个方向 然后可以进行尝试
When is log base b of a 1/2?
什么时候logb(a)等于1/2
Lots of solutions, shout them out.
好多情况 我们来找出来
4 and 2, that is a good one. I better get this right.
4和2 不错 没错的话
Log base 4 of 2 is a half
因为4的平方根是2
because the square root of 4 is 2.
所以以4为底2对数是1/2
So, let's aim for this. Why not?
关注下这个
When would we get log base 4 of 2?
怎么才能得到log4(2)呢
This is b, this is a,
这是b 这是a
so it should be 2T(n/4) plus something.
所以应该是2T(n/4)加上什么东西
And if I want the n^logb(a) to dominate,
如果我想让n^logb(a)占据主导
it has got to be polynomially smaller than root n.
这部分应该多项式地小于n的平方根
So, this should be n^1/2-epsilon.
所以这部分是n^(1/2-ε)
But it could be smaller.
当然可以更小一些
It could be 1. Zero would be nice,
可能是1 当然0更好
but that is probably too much to hope for.
不过 这就想的太美了
So, something smaller,
所以 应该要小一点
strictly polynomially smaller than root n.
多项式地严格小于n开方的多项式
That is our goal. And now comes the magic.
这就是我们目标 见证奇迹时刻到了
If you played with this for a while you would find it,
如果你多研究过这个 你可能发现
I think, at this point.
我觉得在这里
When you know that you are somehow solve this problem of size n
当你解决一个大小为n的问题
with two subproblems of size n/4 what could you do?
两个子问题大小为n/4 你怎么做
Well, if you start thinking of things as squares,
如果你从平方入手的话
this is the natural thing that happens.
这就很自然了
This is called the H layout.
这个叫H布局
You can imagine why.
你可以想一下怎么回事儿
It would be much easier to draw if I had a grid board, a graph board,
要是有个点阵图板的话可能画的轻松些
whatever, if that exists.
如果真有的话
This is a recursive layout.
这是一个递归的布局
I am only going to draw a couple iterations,
我就画两次迭代
but hopefully you can imagine the generalization.
希望你们能想象出一般的情形
I take four Hs,
现在画4个H
a good plan because I want problems of size n/4.
因为我想要问题的大小是n/4
This has n/4 leaves. This has n/4 leaves.
这个有n/4叶节点 这个有n/4叶节点
This is the root, by the way, in the middle.
这个是根节点 在中间
So, I have four problems of size n/4.
现在有4个大小是n/4的问题
Somehow I have got to get that down to two.
我得把它减小到2
Thankfully, if I look at width or if I look at height,
幸运的是 不论是从宽度还是从高度上看
there are only two that matter.
确实只有两个问题
And these two matter and these two get along for free.
这两个 和这两个一起
They are going in parallel, just like we had with height over here.
它们是平行的 就像是和高度这里一样
But I get that both in height and in width.
现在一起得到了高度上和宽度上的结果
If I measure, well, now they are equal,
如果量一下 它们是相等的
so I will just call them the length.
那么可以叫长度
We have L(n)-by-L(n).
现在是L(n)×L(n)
And if I compute well, what is L(n)?
如果算一下 L(n)是多少
I have here L(n/4)
这里是L(n/4)
because there are only a quarter of the leaves
因为这里只有1/4叶节点
in this one or in that one,
这里还有那里
and then I have L(n/4) again.
现在又得到L(n/4)了
So, I get the recurrence that I wanted.
现在得到了我们想要的递归式子了
And that has solution square root of n, as we claimed before.
现在得到我们刚才说的结果n的平方根
Again, we are in Case 1 of the master method.
现在又得到了主方法的第一种情况
Cool, ha? This is a much more compact layout.
很帅吧 这是非常紧凑的布局
Charles, did you invent this layout?
查尔斯 是你发明的这种布局么
No. But I know it appears on your PhD thesis
不是 不过我记得在你的博士论文里有
and you extended it in various directions.
你把它从多个方向上扩展了
So, this is sort of a classic cool layout of trees into grids
这是个传统的树的网格布局的好方法
and another application of divide-and-conquer.
也是分治法思想的另一个应用
I mean this is not particularly useful for algorithms directly.
我意思是不仅在算法上尤其有用
It is useful for VLSI layout directly.
在VLSI布局上也相当有用
But it gives you more flavor of how you should think.
它提供给你更多思考的方式
If you know what running time you are aiming for,
如果你知道你想要的运行时间
like in problem sets in quizzes often
就像小测和作业里面经常出现的
we say here is the running time you have got to get,
规定了你应该得到的运行时间
think about the recurrence that will get you there.
想一想你能得到什么样递归式
And that could inspire you.
会对你有所启发
And that is it. Recitation Friday.
今天就这些 不要忘了周五复习课
Homework lab Sunday. No class Monday.
周日作业实验室开放 周一没有课
See you Wednesday.
下周三再见